<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A prophesie that hath lyen hid, aboue these 2000. yeares Wherein is declared all the most principall matters that hath fallen out, in, and about the ciuill and ecclesiasticall monarchie of Rome, from the rising of Iulius Cæsar, to this present: and which are to be done from hence to the distruction of it, and what shall ensue after that. As the liues and deaths of the emperors. The rising of the ecclesiasticall monarchie. The storie of the greatest enemies of them both with manie other notable accurrences [sic] concerning Germany, France, and Spaine. With the inuasion of the kings of the East.</title>
            <title>Babylon is fallen</title>
            <author>T. L., fl. 1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15111.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108178</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843856</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843856</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8615</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04970)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8615)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 857:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A prophesie that hath lyen hid, aboue these 2000. yeares Wherein is declared all the most principall matters that hath fallen out, in, and about the ciuill and ecclesiasticall monarchie of Rome, from the rising of Iulius Cæsar, to this present: and which are to be done from hence to the distruction of it, and what shall ensue after that. As the liues and deaths of the emperors. The rising of the ecclesiasticall monarchie. The storie of the greatest enemies of them both with manie other notable accurrences [sic] concerning Germany, France, and Spaine. With the inuasion of the kings of the East.</title>
                  <title>Babylon is fallen</title>
                  <author>T. L., fl. 1595.</author>
                  <author>Legate, Thomas, d. ca. 1607, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 50, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Edward Allde] for Nathaniel Fosbrooke, and are to be solde at the west-end of Paules neere to the Bishop of Londons gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Later editions are attributed to T.L., i.e. Thomas Legate?.</note>
                  <note>An anti-Catholic interpretation of the dream in 2 Esdras (Vulgate 4 Esdras) chapter IX.</note>
                  <note>Originally published in 1597 as "Babylon is fallen". This edition has new preliminaries.</note>
                  <note>Title page in red and black.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-G⁴ H² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A discouerye of a prophesie.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, A2v line 2 ends: lock.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 20441 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Apocrypha. --  Esdras, 2nd --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8615:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8615:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PROPHESIE THAT HATH LYEN HID, ABOVE THESE 2000. yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN IS DECLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RED ALL THE MOST PRINCIPALL matters that hath fallen out, in, and about the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and Eccleſiaſticall Monarchie of</hi> Rome, <hi>from the riſing of</hi> Iulius Caeſar, <hi>to this preſent: and which are to be done from hence to the diſtruction of it, and what ſhall enſue after that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS
<list>
                  <item>The liues and deaths of the Emperors.</item>
                  <item>The riſing of the Eccleſiaſticall Monarchie.</item>
                  <item>The ſtorie of the greateſt enemies of them both with manie other notable accurrences concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning GERMANY, FRANCE, and SPAINE.</item>
                  <item>With the inuaſion of the Kings of the EAST.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for NATHANIEL FOSBROOKE, and are to be ſolde at the Weſt-end of Paules Neere to the Biſhop of Londons gate, 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8615:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8615:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eere Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, thinke it not ſtrange I pray thee, that <hi>Eſdras</hi> the Scribe and Prophet of the Lord (in the prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipalleſt of his bookes) ſhould be ſo little regarded:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dani.</hi> 12.6.7.8 9.10.</note> for <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet, prophecying of theſe times, foretelling the wonders that ſhold come to paſſe in them, ſayeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſdras</hi> 12 37.38</note> 
               <hi>That none of the wicked ſhould haue vnderſtanding, but the wiſe ſhall vnderſtand:</hi> And therefore was <hi>Eſdras commaunded to wright thoſe viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he ſaw in a Booke and hide them, &amp; teach them the wiſe of the people, whoſe hearts he knew were able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the wayes of the higheſt:</hi> for as god himſelf doth not ſhew his ſecrets to the vnwiſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.14.</note> ſo no more would he haue the wiſe to whome he ſheweth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to teach them but to the wiſe, leaſt the vnwiſe, not being ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, ſhould ſpurne and barke againſt it: wherefore he ſayeth, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7 6.</note>
               <hi>giue not holy things to dogges,
neither caſt ye your pearles before the Swine.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And as wiſedome is iuſtified of her Children,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 11.19.</note> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe it is wiſedome, and for no other reſpecte, ſo the vnwiſe reſiſt it, becauſe their tongues cannot taſte it, nor their ſtomackes digeſt it,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2 14.15.</note> it being hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
<pb facs="tcp:8615:3"/>and they earthly, who iudge things by earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reaſon. Therefore hath God ſeene it good to lock vp, and hide his treaſures and richeſt iewels, in moſt ſecret places, that the dilligent ſearchers for wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome might onely finde them out, and that fooles might be fooles as they pleaſe to be,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 2.3.4.5.</note> though wiſe in their owne conceits.</p>
            <p>The Booke of Wiſedome which hath it name ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it nature; who knoweth not with what vehemency it is reſiſted, although it be the very flood of <hi>Salomons</hi> wiſdome. If <hi>Iohn,</hi> The greateſt that was borne of women,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 11</note> and Chriſt his Lord the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome, were iudged (of the vnwiſe children) to be poſſeſt of diuels, what maruell though <hi>Salomon</hi> and <hi>Eſdras</hi> with other prophets and righteous men, be blaſphemouſly delt withall?</p>
            <p>But the principall cauſe pretended is, for that it was not found compiled with other ſcriptures in the Hebrew tongue, for which cauſe they may aſwell exclude ſome part of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the greateſt part of the new Teſtament: but they ſay it is full of lyes, and was neuer cannonized: darſt thou ſay ſo? Becauſe the wiſedome of the vnwiſe neuer cannonis'd it, did the children of wiſedome therefore neuer approue it? If all be current that hath bene cannonized, Then many deuils ſhall goe to heauen, &amp; much falſehood ſhall ſtand for truth: and if all be lyes that is not can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonized, then much truth ſhall periſh, and many Saints goe to hell: For ſome of the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles, As the ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>Peter,</hi> and the two
<pb facs="tcp:8615:3"/>laſt Epiſtles of <hi>Iohn, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iudes</hi> Epiſtles were for a long time not receiued generally, and many hundred Saints were neuer cannonized,
<note place="margin">By the Church of Rome.</note> wheras ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vncleane lyers and murth erers were: and dareſt thou blaſpheme the truth and accuſe it of lies for theſe cauſes? If Charity did rule thy heart, and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome gouerne thy minde, thou wouldeſt labour to reconcile it with the other ſcriptures, which, if men be ſo diſpoſed, they may alſo cauill againſt. But let men take heede what they doe, let them not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne that they know not, nor call that a lye which they vnderſtand not. If I ſhould ſay Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpake vnaduiſedly, when he ſayeth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 21.25.</note> 
               <hi>(There are alſo many things that Ieſus did, which if they had bene all written, I ſuppoſe the world could not containe the bookes)</hi> did I not belye the holy Apoſtle? If time prooue that to be of God which I in my ignorant boldnes, blaſpheme and ſpeake againſt, ſhall I eſcape vnpuniſhed by that truth? let me therefore take heede and feare, and as I may not take vpon me to affirm that I know not, ſo let me take heede that I condemne not that which I conceiue not; eſpecially ſuch holy writings wherein ſuch great wiſedome doth conſiſt, leaſt for a words ſake that I vnderſtand not, I depriue my ſelfe of a great benefit that I might enioy. For if time prooue it to be of God (as ſure it will) what ſhall I then excuſe my ſelfe withall? was not the Reuelation of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> doubted of (by many) a great while, &amp; is it not now receiued as a moſt deuine Prophecy,? So ſhal it be f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd in time, that none of al the Prophets
<pb facs="tcp:8615:4"/>of ould, did excell this Prophet <hi>Eſdras,</hi> nor ſee more ſecrets, nor prophecie more plainely of Ieſus Chriſt, and of the miſteries of the Goſpell then he. And alſo greater wiſedome is not to be found in all <hi>Salomons</hi> writings, then is in the book of Wiſedome ſo much condemned, why ſhould we not iuſtifie the truth for it owne ſake, and not ſhake it off, and take it vp, vpon ſuch colde and weake occaſions?</p>
            <p>If the maieſty and truth of the other Scriptures did not plead for it ſelfe, Time alſo bringing foorth all the <hi>Hebrues, Grecians, Latiniſts,</hi> and <hi>Cannoniſers</hi> in the world could neuer make it good therfore let truth ſpeake, and wiſdome vtter her voyce, and let time bring foorth as they haue euer done, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them not, and if thou be one of wiſedomes chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, receiue it.</p>
            <p>And although there be too many that dooth take vpon them to diſcouer prophecies, whoſe falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods time will diſcouer, yet there is a worke which is of God, and that ſhall ſtand mauger the ſpight of all it enemies: and let them that dare ſo boldly rage and rayle againſt it, knowe, that when the day doth declare it, they ſhall be aſhamed, and wiſh they had held their tongues.</p>
            <p>Thus I thought good to aduertiſe thee by the way, leaſt at the firſt ſight of enuied <hi>Eſdras,</hi> thou ſhouldſt be diſmayed: Enuied (I ſay) by enuious ſpirits, but approued of God and of his holy ones. I will ſay no more for him at this time, he is at hand, let him now ſpeake for himſelfe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:8615:4"/>
            <head>The contents of the Prophecie.</head>
            <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He liues and deaths of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ryſing of the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Monarchie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſtorie of the greateſt enemies of them both, with their principall actions, and of their ouerthrow and ends.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Of the three kingdomes, Germanie, France and Spaine, Roomes long approoned truſty friends, and their ſeuerall ends &amp; deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And how that Roome ſhall be burnt with fire, and when:</p>
            <p n="6">6. The earth refreſhed, and Iſraell reſtored to life.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The comming downe of the Turke and his Army vpon Chriſtendome, till fire come downe from heauen vpon them.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ierem: 20.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For I haue heard the raylings of many, and how they watch for my halting, ſaying, it may be that he is deceiued.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prophecy">
            <pb facs="tcp:8615:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8615:5"/>
            <head>A DISCOVERYE OF A PROPHESIE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eſdras</hi> 4. Chap 11.</bibl>
                  <p>Then I ſawe a dreame. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>1</label>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>FTER this, the Prophet ſaw a viſion, concerning the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, continuance, &amp; fall of th'Empire and ſupremacie of Rome. And this viſion was ſhewed him in the dayes of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> King of Perſia, about <hi>400.</hi> yeares before the firſt ſtone of her Empire was laide.
<note place="margin">Iu. Ceſar.</note>
            </p>
            <q>And behold, there aroſe from
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8615:6"/>the Sea an Eagle.</q>
            <p>And there aroſe among the Nations, the fierce and fearefull Kingdome and Empire of Rome, ſeene in viſion by the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> ſome few yeares before.</p>
            <q>Which had 12. feathered winges.</q>
            <p>Wherein ſhould ariſe and reigne <hi>12.</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, which ſhould ſpred their power like winges ouer all the earth, in great feare ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on it. And it ſeemed good vnto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to touch by an intellection theſe <hi>12.</hi> only, both for they are a Iewrye ſufficient to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue the whole ſuite of Emperors which did ariſe &amp; raigne in her: as alſo becauſe they on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were natiue Romans, deſcended of the <hi>Iulij, Seruij, Saluij, Flauij, &amp;c.</hi> vnlike therein vnto the reſt, which were all (or almoſt all) like changeable ſtuffe of diuers colours, ſo of diuers Nations. Their riſing, continuance, and end, is toucht in their proper place.</p>
            <q>And three heads.</q>
            <p>Her three heads are three Kingdomes,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8615:6"/>fore-ordained to vpholde and maintaine the power of her pride, when all her winges and feathers ſhould faile her. And are reſerued to execute her laſt will, and finiſhe her fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, as ſhalbe hereafter more at full decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>2</label> And I ſaw, and beholde, ſhe ſpread her winges ouer all the earth, &amp; all the winds of the ayre gathered themſelues and blew on her.</q>
            <p>By the windes, are meant her proſperous and happie ſucceſſe in all her proceedings. And of neceſſitie it muſt goe well with her, whom euery winde doth blowe to good. Witnes the limits of her territories, from <hi>Ganges</hi> to <hi>Gades,</hi> and from the <hi>Scythian Sea</hi> vnto the <hi>Cape of Hope:</hi> as teſtifieth one of her own, which ſaith: that ſhe extended her tents, to the borders of the Ocean, and the feare of her name vnto the heauens.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>3</label> And I ſaw, that out of her fethers grew vp other contrarie fethers,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8615:7"/>but they became litle fethers and ſmall.</q>
            <p>And the Prophet ſaw, that among the Princes and gouernors which ruled in her, there aroſe and grew vp certain Kings, which were contrary vnto her, marking ſuch as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to roote vp the crown and dignitie of her Empire, to plant themſelues therin, &amp; their houſe for euer. But their thoughts preuailed not, for as the verſe concludeth, their power waned, and they periſhed like the reſt: what thoſe contrary Kings were; their number, names, attempts and end, ſhalbe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered in their place.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>4</label> But her heads reſted, and the head in the midſt was greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> th'other heads, yet reſted it with them.</q>
            <p>But the three kingdomes fore-apointed t'accompliſh &amp; finiſh the wickednes of this great Citie, were quiet and at reſt, as not yet (during the reigne of her fethers) conceaued and brought forth. And the Prophet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued that th'oue of thoſe Kings was greater in power then both his fellowes, yet reſted it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8615:7"/>with them. Concerning theſe three Kings, their names, their greatnes, and al that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth, ſhal be ſpoken in due place.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>5</label> Then I ſaw, and behold, the Eagle flew with her fethers, and reigned vpon earth and ouer them that dvvelt therin.</q>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>6</label> And I ſavv that all things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen vvere ſubiect vnto her, and no man ſpake againſt her, no not one creature vpon earth.</q>
            <p>And the Prophet beheld, that this proud citie flew with her Emperors and Legions ouer all her neighbors, ſubiecting all the dwellers on earth vnder her, in ſuch ſort, as there was not a Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or People to be found vnder heauen, that was not either rooted out by her, or inforced to receiue their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors from her.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>7</label> And I ſavv that the Eagle ſtood vp vpon her clavves, and ſpake
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8615:8"/>to her feathers ſaying:</q>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>8</label> VVatch not altogether, ſleep euery one in his ovvn place, and vvatch by courſe.</q>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>9</label> But let the heads be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for the laſt.</q>
            <p>And the Prophet obſerued, that this power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Citie, in the daies wherein (ouergorged with pride) ſhe ſtood vpon terms of her coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and armes, tooke ſuch order (for in euill ſhe was very methodicall) that her Kings and Kayſers, ſhould neither ſleep nor watch, that is neither periſh nor rule all at once, but riſe in a ſucceſſiue courſe, as in the verſes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing is manifeſted. And ſhe further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that the three laſt Kingdomes, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to conclude the number of her ſinnes, ſhould take their eaſe and not awake, till their time appointed.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>10</label> Neuertheleſſe, I ſavve that the voice vvent not out of her heads but from the middeſt of her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye.</q>
            <p>As hee that vndertakes a dangerous leape
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8615:8"/>doth firſt retire, the better to aduance his ſtrength: ſo to bound fairlye ouer the dacke vnderſtanding of theſe words, we muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie looke backe &amp; carry before vs the true birth and perfect nature of this Empire: which the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> in his viſion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigneth vnder the forme of a ten-horned beaſt, ſignifying thereby, that it ſhould be a power vpheld by a ſucceſſion of many Kinges: for the hornes betoken Kings, and the number of <hi>10.</hi> comprehends all, be they neuer ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as all numbers are contained vnder <hi>10.</hi> or made of their reduplication be they neuer ſo infinit. And addeth further, that his teeth were of iron, his nails of braſſe, inferring ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, the vnreſiſtable force of his legions and Leaders. And proceding ſaith, that there aroſe amongſt his Kings, one of an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtrange nature, ſignifying by that one, a ſtrange race and ſucceſſion of Princes, far differing in ſhape and forme of regiment from al their predeceſſors, obtaining dominion not by iron teeth and braſen nails, as did th' Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors which aroſe before them, but by diſceit and by a mouth which ſpake preſumptuous things againſt the moſt High, blaſpheming his name, his Tabernacle, &amp; them that dwel in heauen, who by a hidden &amp; vnknown force, ſhould ſubdue the third part of the world, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, al <hi>Europe</hi> with her Princes. By which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8615:9"/>deliniation, it is euident, that the holy-Ghoſt accounteth the chalenged prerogatiue &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie of Rome, all one power, all one Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, whether it obtaine the ſpoile by force, or by fraud, that is, by power of Emperors, or craſt of Popes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Cha.</hi> 7.24</hi>
               </note> who ſhould be far vnlike them, as <hi>Daniel</hi> himſelfe ſaith: <hi>And he ſhall be vnlike to the firſt.</hi> Meaning in forme of clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, obteining &amp; maintaining Iurisdiction, not in pride, purpoſe and determination. So as we may beholde ſuch an vnlikely likenes betweene them, as was betweene the two Siſters, of whome it is ſaid,
<q>
                  <l>—facies non omnibus vna,</l>
                  <l>nec diuerſa tamen, qualem decet eſſe Sororum.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much concerning the Prophet <hi>Daniels</hi> deſcription of the Empire of Rome: whence we note, that the ſame power which <hi>Daniel</hi> there deſcribeth by a beaſt with horns, teeth and nails: our Prophet here doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liniate by an Eagle, with wings, fethers and heads: whoſe imperiall winges after they were ſo clipt, as ſhe could no longer fly ouer all in her proper colours, and ſtile of <hi>Roma tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omfante:</hi> deuiſed how by diſceit ſhe might vphold her throne (for to be high was all her care) and found nothing ſo fit as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe her ſelfe, &amp; chalenge prelation vnder the maske of <hi>Roma la Santa.</hi> And this is it which this Verſe teacheth, that when the ſinfull
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8615:9"/>Citie ſaw her feathers ſo pluckt, as the feare of her armes and forces, might no longer flye into al kingdoms, commanding them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the paine of <hi>Imperium Romanum:</hi> Lying by meanes of this diſtres, verye weake and in danger of falling, her counſell and bodie politique, deuiſed by lyes and witch-crafte (wherein was all her pleaſure from her youth) to reſtore the ſupremacye and honor of her name, vnder the colour of <hi>Eccleſia Dei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherin this race of preſumptuous horns excelled the ſinne of all the hornes that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ruled in her, for they, as in whom Satan dwelt but literally, did but in open hoſtilitie fight againſt the higheſt, ſetting before him a god made of a wicked man, whoſe fathers bloud cryeth out for vengeance night and daye, whoſe bedfellow was <hi>&amp; Soror &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iux,</hi> and whoſe wife was <hi>id quod dicere nolo.</hi> But this race of preſumptuous and deceitfull Kinges, as in whome Satan dwelleth ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuallye, in a hidden treaſure of blaſphemy, ſets vp the Higheſt againſt himſelfe, and vnder the viſar of the Church, and the name of God, blaſphemeth his Sanctuary, and the Lord thereof. No meruaile then, tho ſhe and Syon be at ods, for as golde can bodye it ſelfe with any mettall liquifiable, latten excepted, which notwithſtanding in outward face and ſhew of all mettals is moſt like vnto it: ſo, no
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8615:10"/>Church is more capitall enemie to the true Church, then ſhee, who in outward geſture, grace and countenance, is likeſt like the chaſt and virgin ſpouſe, and is indeed a whore.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>11</label> Then I numbred her contrary fethers, and behold they were eight of them.</q>
            <p>In the third verſe of this Chapter, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet made mention of theſe contrary fethers, which in their thoughts conſpirde to raiſe their houſe with the ruins of Rome. And heere proceedeth more perticularly to declare their number, foretelling there ſhould be eight of them, whom we will heere call out by name that if occaſion ſerue, wee maye the better knowe them.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt were Meſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gothes, vnder the leading of <hi>Alaricus.</hi> The ſecond Hunns,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> whoſe King was <hi>Attalas.</hi> The third Vandals,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> their head, <hi>Genſerick.</hi> The fourth <hi>Odoacer.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4-5"/> The fift Eaſt-gothes, their chiefe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <hi>Theodorick.</hi> The ſixt <hi>Totilas,</hi> bred in Spaine, with ſuch followers as for thoſe times that Country yelded.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſeuenth Longobards, with their guid <hi>Alboinus.</hi> The eight and laſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
               <hi>a home conſpiracie,</hi> more to be fear'd (as all included diſeaſes are moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous) then all the reſt.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:8615:10"/>
            <p>And altho many others beſides theſe, as <hi>Radagaiſe,</hi> the <hi>Alani</hi> now called <hi>Almans,</hi> the <hi>Burgonians</hi> conducted by <hi>Gundibald,</hi> the <hi>Vngers, Saracens,</hi> &amp;c. were all in their time as coſtly enemies to the Empire as ſome of theſe, yet none did humble the great Citie, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of wickednes but theſe eight only. And therefore the reſt may not be allowed to ſit at this table, but may ſerue to iuſtifie the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Beaſt, which was thus wounded againe and ſtricken of all, as ſhe had woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſtricken all.</p>
            <p>And if in reading doubt ariſe, how theſe eight fethers may be contrary to the Eagle, that is, reſiſters of her power and dominion, and yet be fethers of the Eagle, that is, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teiners of the ſame: The anſwer is, that they were aduerſaries and contrary vnto her, as ſhe ſtood vpon termes of <hi>Imperium orbis terrae:</hi> but after ſhe had changed her coppie, and claimed ſupremacie vnder the cloake of <hi>Mater Eccleſia,</hi> they were for the moſt main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teiners of her pride, and became drunke alſo with her worſhip, as other Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of th'earth.</p>
            <p>And thus much for their number, and names, their ſeuerall attempts, their proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities and ende, ſhalbe preſented in their place.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:8615:11"/>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>12</label> After this I ſaw, and beholde vpon the right ſide there aroſe one fether, and raigned ouer all the earth.</q>
            <p>This fether here deſcribed is the firſt of the twelue, namely <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> who (like an ill interpreter) tranſlated <hi>Senatum Populum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Romanum,</hi> into <hi>Caeſarem Auguſtum.</hi> Whoſe Image, which in this verſe is ſo liuely reſembled, conſiſteth of <hi>2.</hi> features: the firſt, ſheweth the manner of his riſing, in theſe words.</p>
            <q>And behold, vpon the right ſide there aroſe one feather.</q>
            <p>Which ſerue in ſtead of art, to diſcouer the very true lines, and caſt of his happines.</p>
            <p>For the houſe of <hi>Cornelij</hi> was as eloquent as he, and <hi>Marius</hi> doubtles as good a leader as he, and <hi>Catilin</hi> as nobly borne as he, and all theſe aroſe t'inuade the common-wealth, and to tranſlate it into a Kingdome as well as he, but none of them roſe on the right ſide but he. And thus much for the manner of this ſpeech; ſo we take this with-all, that theſe words <hi>(right ſide)</hi> in their naturall and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per intent, do ſignifie (as through all this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8615:11"/>Chapter) the ſureſt and ſtrongeſt ſide.</p>
            <p>The ſecond feature in this reſemblance to be obſerued, is his power, ſet forth in theſe words. <hi>And he reigned ouer all the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For after he had ſubdued <hi>France,</hi> broken the heart of <hi>Germany,</hi> made his name knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>England,</hi> be returned into <hi>Italie,</hi> ouerthrew the great Protector of the libertie <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Pompey</hi> and his hoſt, in the fields of <hi>Pharſalie.</hi> And like the fire of heauen (as one of her Pocts ſaith) with ſuch celeritie drew after the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of that ſtricken faction, both in <hi>Africa</hi> &amp; <hi>Spaine,</hi> that in two yeares ſpace he brought to pas, that nether citie nor creature durſt open againſt him: which done, he aſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Italie,</hi> and tooke vpon him as Lord thereof, triumphing in the ſpoiles of the world, and the blood of his Country.</p>
            <p>And knowing that the name of a King (which he ſo much affected) was odious to the quality and nature of that People: inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the gouernment vnder the maske of a perpetual Dictator, preſeruing therunder (for he was wiſe aboue all the fethers) ſome hope of recouering their late ſlaine liberty, but indeed eſtabliſhing a kingdome from which it could neuer redeeme it ſelfe againe.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8615:12"/>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>13</label> And when it had reigned the end of it came, and the place thereof appeered no more.</q>
            <p>But this new-borne proſperitie (as is the nature of all this worldes felicitie) laſted but a while; for in the third yeare of his Dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatorſhip, he was ſlaine in the Senat, by the conſpiration of <hi>24.</hi> of whom the moſt both in his own (ſo dangerous is the name of truſt) and other mens opinions, were thought his chiefeſt frendes. And thus was this fether blowen awaye, after it had inioyed his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>56.</hi> yeares, and raigned <hi>3.</hi> A man for let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, armes and counſell, famous far aboue all his ſucceeders, and in diſcreete bounty, and Princely clemencie (rare vertues in ſuch a fortune) without controuerſie, ſurpaſſing all Princes made of earth.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>14</label> So the next ſtoode vp and rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned, and it continued a long time, but after it had reigned his end alſo came, and as the firſt it appeered no more.</q>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:8615:12"/>
            <p>Next after him aroſe <hi>Octauius,</hi> the ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted ſonne of <hi>Iulius:</hi> otherwiſe alſo neere him in blood, as being the ſonne of his neece <hi>Accia,</hi> who hauing taken reuenge vpon the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of his father, and obtained in all his warres, forreine and at home: triumphed Lord ouer all, adding to his fathers pompe (which he had bought ſo deer) the honors of <hi>Parens Patriae,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this fether continued (as the Prophet ſaw) a long time, for it reigned <hi>Triumuir</hi> with <hi>Anthonie</hi> and <hi>Lepidus</hi> two yeares, and as <hi>Duumuir</hi> with <hi>Anthonie</hi> alone ten yeare, and then deuouring his fellow in a Sea-fight at <hi>Actium,</hi> reigned all alone <hi>44.</hi> yeares.</p>
            <p>But after it had reigned, his end alſo came, and as the Prophet concludeth) he diſcended like the firſt, and appeered no more. For by the treaſon of <hi>Liuia</hi> his wife, impatient to tarie th'inthronizing of her ſonne (as is the nature of ambition the nerer the goale, the faſter it runnes) his lingring ſoule was taken from him at <hi>Nola,</hi> in the <hi>70.</hi> and ſixth yeare of his tranſgreſſion, when he had reigned <hi>20.</hi> leſſe.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>15</label> Then there came a voice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and ſaid.</q>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>16</label> Hear thou that haſt kept the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8615:13"/>earth ſo long, this I ſay vnto thee, before thou beginſt t'appeere no more.</q>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>17</label> Ther ſhal none after thee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto thy time, nor yet to the halfe thereof.</q>
            <p>That we may know ther is no God like vnto the Higheſt, who only holdeth the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and times of all thinges in his hand, the Prophet foreſheweth, that none of the twelue ſhould continue like to <hi>Octauius,</hi> nor yet attaine vnto halfe his time: which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word of the Lord was accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſbed: for his ſonne <hi>Tiberius</hi> of all the reſt rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned longeſt, and longer by eight yeares then any of the reſt, and yet could not attaine to halfe the time of his father, which deſcended before him.</p>
            <p>That God only might be honoured in all his workes, and iuſtified when he ſpeaketh.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>18</label> Then aroſe the third, and rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned as th'other afore, and it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peered no more alſo.</q>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:8615:13"/>
            <p>Then ſtept vp <hi>Tiberius,</hi> and reigned in great abhomination, as did his fathers before him, but after a while he diſcended alſo, and appee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no more. He all his skill in ſortilege and wisdome mathematicall, wherunto he had ſold himſelfe from his youth, could either fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell or fore-warne him of <hi>Caius</hi> his nephew, by whome he was poyſoned, in the <hi>70.</hi> and <hi>8.</hi> yeare of his mortalitie, and three and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tith of his raigne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>19</label>
               <hi>And ſo came it to all th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, one after an other, ſo that euery one reigned, and then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peered no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like ſort (ſaith the Prophet) did all the reſt which of the <hi>12.</hi> remained, ſucceſſiuely riſe, reigne, and periſh.</p>
            <p>Of whome the firſt,
<note place="margin">Caligula.</note> in blaſphemy excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, was murthered by the Captaine of his guard, after he had ſat in the chaire of the ſcornefull <hi>29.</hi> yeares, and in the throne of his fathers almoſt <hi>4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond, only wiſe in euill,
<note place="margin">Claudius.</note> was poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his inceſtuous wife his neece <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pina,</hi> in the <hi>64.</hi> yeare of his filthines, and <hi>14.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:8615:14"/>of his reigne.</p>
            <p>The third,
<note place="margin">Nero.</note> a monſter, deformed in life, in mariage, and end: his life ſcornefull to the height of his fathers, his mariage thrice more deteſtable, his end more vnnaturall then any of theirs: for after he had reigned in ſinne fourteene yeares, and ſinne in him eighteene more, fel by his own ſword into the graue of his fathers, and in him deſcended the houſe of the <hi>Iulij.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth was of an other extraction,
<note place="margin">Galba.</note> but not of a better, deſcended of the antient familie of the <hi>Sulpitij,</hi> roſe vp late, but pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed early: for he was <hi>60.</hi> and <hi>3.</hi> yeares olde before he taſted the Empire, which he got and loſt in <hi>7.</hi> moneths.</p>
            <p>The fifth likewiſe of a new houſe,
<note place="margin">Otho.</note> but of the old building, got poſſeſſion by the bloud of his Predeceſſor, and by ſpilling his owne in three moneths and od daies, loſt it againe, after he had walkte in the abhomination of his fathers, eight and thirtie yeares.</p>
            <p>The ſixt alſo,
<note place="margin">Vitellius.</note> was new and olde, in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (ſaue gluttony) excelling his fellowes, in life and death like filthie: deſcended in the eight moneth of his tyrannie, after he had wearied himſelfe in the pleaſures of Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum (where firſt his youth was branded) <hi>7.</hi> and <hi>50.</hi> yeares.</p>
            <p>After him aroſe the ſeuenth,
<note place="margin">Veſpatian.</note> who bought
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8615:14"/>the crowne with the bloud of his M. and ware it in baſe couetouſnes ten yeares, but then was likewiſe blowen down, hauing full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fild the pleaſures of <hi>59.</hi> more.</p>
            <p>The eight was he which executed the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance due to the great murtherers,
<note place="margin">Titus.</note> the earthly Hieruſalem: who in the <hi>40.</hi> yeare of his pleaſure, after he had reigned <hi>2.</hi> yeares and ſo many moneths, was alſo blowen down, not without the ſuſpected treaſon of his brother, and ſucceſſour.</p>
            <p>The ninth and laſt,
<note place="margin">Domitian</note> and (if it were poſſible) the worſt of all, who after he had reigned in the luſt of his Fathers <hi>15.</hi> yeares, and liued therein <hi>30.</hi> more, was murthered by the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of his chamber, and beaten downe after the reſt which deſcended before him. So that euerie one of them (as this verſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſted) reigned, and then appeered no more.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>20</label> Then I looked and behold in proceſſe of time, the fethers that followed ſtood vp on the right ſide, that they might rule alſo, &amp; ſome of them ruled, but within a while they appeered no more.</q>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:8615:15"/>
            <p>And the Prophet obſerued and ſaw (after the twelue were deſcended) the Emperors that followed to riſe, that they might rule alſo; and as many of them as roſe on the right ſide, that is: in the ſtrength and power of the twelue, did in their place (according to the proclamation publiſhed in the eight verſe) ſpred their winges and reigne alſo, as
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nerua.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Traian.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Adrian.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Antoninus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marcus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Commodus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pertinax.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iulian.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Seuerus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Caracalla.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Macrinus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Heliogabalus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexander.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Maximinus.</hi> And the reſt, to the third <hi>Valentinian.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In whoſe daies, the power of the Eagle was ſo wounded, by th'incurſion and ſaccage of the two firſt contrary fethers, that ſhe could neuer after recure her ſelfe again but lay ſicke and kept the chamber ſome ten genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which alſo laſted but twice ſo many yeares, to the riſing of <hi>Momillus</hi> in whome
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8615:15"/>deſcended all that was left of the Empire, name, and tittle for euer.</p>
            <p>So that all the fethers which the Prophet beheld in proceſſe of time to follow the <hi>12.</hi> and in their ſtrength, their ſinne and crueltie, to defile the earth: namely from <hi>Domitian,</hi> to the third <hi>Valentinian,</hi> were <hi>50.</hi> and <hi>3.</hi> Kings. All which in a while (as this verſe conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth) vaniſhed like the <hi>12.</hi> and appeared no more.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>21</label> And ſome of them were ſet vp, but ruled not.</q>
            <list>
               <head>As,</head>
               <item>
                  <hi> Vindex.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Piſcenius Niger.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Albinus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Diadumenus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maximus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Balbinus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>30.</hi> Tirants.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firmus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Saturninus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Proculus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bonoſus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eugenius.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quintillus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rufinus.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:8615:16"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conſtantinus non Magnus.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Heraclianus,</hi> and others, as in the deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of times, may more plainly appeare.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>22</label> After this I looked, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, the twelue fethers appee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no more.</q>
            <p>Vnder the <hi>12.</hi> winges or fethers (for both betoken one) are comprehended by an intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection (as in the firſt verſe) all, which in the ſtrength of the twelue followed, from <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> to the third <hi>Valentinian,</hi> who periſhed in the yeare <hi>455.</hi> after he had reigned <hi>30.</hi> and liued <hi>5.</hi> more.</p>
            <p>And thus according to promiſe made in the firſt verſe, is preſented a tragicall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all the Eagles winges, from her firſt fether <hi>Iul. Caeſar,</hi> in whome the power of her pride began, to the third <hi>Valentinian,</hi> with whome it ended: who after they had ſhewed themſelues, and trodden down the earth <hi>500.</hi> &amp; <hi>30.</hi> yeares, they departed for euer the ſtage of this world, and all their pompe and glorie deſcended, and appeered no more.</p>
            <p>And here my pen like to the earth which being deliuered from her oppreſſors, did thirſt to be refreſhed: ſo hauing ouercome this part of her taſke, did think to and ſome eaſe, but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8615:16"/>in their hopes they are both deceiued, for after the Eagles fethers decended, the ſorrowes of the earth increaſed more and more, and ther aroſe (as ſeldome comes the better) a race of <hi>Sodomiticall,</hi> and <hi>vnnaturall</hi> Kings, who vnder the viſar of Succeſſors to <hi>Peter,</hi> and vicars to the <hi>Lamb,</hi> ſo far excelled the whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of their fathers the Emperors (whoſe Vicars and Succeſſors indeed they are) that they inforced the Higheſt, to poure his deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined vengeance, vpon the children of men. Who according to the iudgement fore-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by his ſeruant <hi>Iohn,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <hi>Reuel.</hi> 16.</hi>
                  </note> Poured out his wrath vpon the Sea, that it became like to the blood of the dead:</hi> that is to ſay, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great Citie and Empres of the world, by ſcourge after ſcourge (as how often and greuous in the vew of her contrary fethers may appeere) ſo at the the full auenging himſelfe, that there was not a drop of <hi>Roman</hi> blood to be founde on earth, theſe many hundreth yeares.</p>
            <p>And as the defection and vncleannes was generall, ſo was the puniſhment: for (as the Apoſtle in the ſame chapter propheſieth) <hi>The wrath of the higheſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <hi>Reuel.</hi> 16</hi>
                  </note> was poured out vpon the riuers and fountaines likewiſe, and they were turned into blood alſo,</hi> that is: vpon all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Nations whatſoeuer, in ſuch ſort, as ther is not a kingdome this day on earth to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8615:17"/>found, that hath not bin (ſince the riſing of the beaſt) cut downe by ſword, and yeelded her ſtock to ſtrange griffes, as by the bloody Regiſters of euery perticular Nation doth ſo cleerly appeere, as if it were written with the beames of the Sunne.</p>
            <p>And as the dayes were euill aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſo they exceeded in darknes &amp; ignorance: that my pen hath no leſſe trouble, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered of the reſt of her labor, then had the then-dwellers on-earth, to indure the paines of their oppreſſion and trauell: but to take into my way againe, the Prophet addeth.
<q>Nor the two winges.</q>
Figuring by the two winges, the two firſt contrary fethers, <hi>Alaricus,</hi> and <hi>Attalas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt aroſe in the <hi>19.</hi> of <hi>Honorius,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor to the third <hi>Valentinian:</hi> And was the firſt that ſlewe the great Citie, the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of all the world, meaſuring her by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, ſworde, and fire: according to the ſquare whereby ſhee had iudged others almoſt <hi>12.</hi> hundreth yeares. Which wofull end (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beginning of her wofull end) made a certaine antient friend of hers, bewailing the night wherein ſhee was ſmitten, to crye, <note place="margin">Hierom.</note>
               <hi>Nocte Moab capta eſt, nocte cecidit murus eius, quis cladem illius noctis, quis funera fando
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8615:17"/>explicet?</hi> And when this feather had thus troden downe the pride of the Eagle, in the yeare <hi>410.</hi> a <hi>1157.</hi> yeares after <hi>Romulus</hi> had raiſed her walles, with the blood of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: proceeded to rip vp her bowels, ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and burning her principall partes, <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, Campania, Apulia, Lucania, Calabria,</hi> where raging in his higheſt thoughtes, deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing now to ſpred his glory ouer all, was by ſuddeine death blowen away, and his place appeered no more.</p>
            <p>Th'other aroſe in the <hi>27.</hi> of the third <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian,</hi> in greater feare then did the firſt, deuouring at his entrance all that reſt of <hi>Italie</hi> which <hi>Alaricus</hi> had left vneaten, <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leia, Verona, Mantua, Cremona, Brixia, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia,</hi> with all the now territorie of Venice: but by the cunning dealing of the deceitfull King, whoſe name was then Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> was intreated to ſel the great Citie, and to depart <hi>Italie,</hi> which he left as a waſt, ſtinking in her fierie ruins, &amp; ſo repaſſing the <hi>Danube,</hi> retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into his Scythia againe: where the yeare following in top of his fulnes, was in a night found ſtrangled in his owne blood, wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he was diſolued, by the intemperate vſe of a wedding feaſt, and a new ſpouſe.</p>
            <p>And thus periſhed this ſonne of <hi>Mundzuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> the ſcourge of God, and terror of men (for ſo he called himſelfe) and which not only
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8615:18"/>the fiers of <hi>Italie,</hi> but his very ſhape may well iuſtifie: for he is deſcribed a man of litle ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſquare ſet, great head, litle eyes, thin hair'd, thinner bearded, a noſe great and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, his colour foule and gypſon-like.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>23</label> And ther was no more vpon the Eagles body, but two heads that reſted and ſix winges.</q>
            <p>And ther were no more triumphing fethers to be found on her, for all her glorious power was decended to two weak and feeble heads, which for they reigned not in the ſtrength of their predeceſſors, the Prophet daineth not to call ruling fethers, but reſting heads.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Martian.</note>Th'one ſlept in th'eaſt at Conſtantinople,
whom <hi>Genſerick</hi> the third contrary fether, not long before had diſhonorably taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Valentin.</note>Th'other in the weſt at Rauenna,
taken with ſuch a Lethargy, that he neither heard nor felt the Maſſacre of Vngarie, committed by <hi>Hunns:</hi> nor the loud and pitifull crie of his cheefeſt Prouinces, Spaine and Africa, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured by <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals;</hi> nor the teares and deepe lament of Gaule and Britanie, ouerflowen with <hi>Franks</hi> and <hi>Angles,</hi> people
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8615:18"/>from beyond the Rhene, who not only with their blood and poſteritie, but with their name alſo haue ſtain'd both kingdomes to this day. So as the Prophet well conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, ther was no more to be found vpon the Eagles bodie, but theſe two drowſie heads, which refted, and ſix contrary fethers, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>
                        <hi>Genſerique.</hi> 1</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>
                        <hi>Odoacer.</hi> 2</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>
                        <hi>Theodorick.</hi> 3</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>
                        <hi>Totilas.</hi> 4</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The <hi>
                        <hi>Longobards.</hi> 5</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And th'<hi>
                        <hi>inteſtine faction.</hi> 6</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> of which, in the verſes following.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>24</label> Then ſaw I alſo, the two winges deuided them-ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſix, and remained vnder the head that was vpon the right ſide, but the foure continued in their place.</q>
            <p>And the Prophet ſaw, that two of the ſix de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-ſelues in counſell &amp; manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> th'other foure: for wheras the four ſought to be Lords of Rome in fee, reſoluing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8615:19"/>in their thoughts, t'extinguiſh the name and maieſtie of her Empire for euer, theſe <hi>2.</hi> were of an other minde, for they agreed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine vnder the countenance and fauour of the Eagles right head, contented to weare a crowne tho with leaue of it: meaning by the right head th'eaſt Empire, ſo called, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it was far ſtronger in power then the weſt: whoſe broad-ſpreading honor (as in the verſe fore-going) was now become a ſtarueling, onlie his name and appellation continued ſome ten ſucceſſions, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1 <hi>Valentinian.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2 <hi>Maximus.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3 <hi>Auitus.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4 <hi>Maiorianus.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5 <hi>Seuerus.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6 <hi>Anthemius.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7 <hi>Olybrius.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>8 <hi>Glycerius.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>9 <hi>Iulius Nepos.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>10 <hi>Momyllus.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Which all alſo vaniſhed (as before is toucht) in <hi>20.</hi> yeares. And the Eagles pompe which was at full in <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> was enterred with <hi>Auguſtulus</hi> (for ſo was <hi>Momyllus</hi> called) and with him deſcended the name and title of <hi>Imperium Romanum</hi> for euer.</p>
            <p>And the two winges thus deuided in pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie from the foure, were <hi>Genſerick</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8615:19"/>
               <hi>Theodorick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which the firſt, trained into Italie by treaſon of the Empres, entred Rome <hi>43.</hi> yeares after ſhe had bin hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled by the <hi>Gothes,</hi> and led into captiuitie all her treaſor, and (as is the fatall reward of ſuch offenders (the traitres alſo her-ſelfe. And after <hi>14.</hi> daies thus loaden, departed into his <hi>Africa</hi> againe: wher-ouer he reigned in peace and pleaſure <hi>51.</hi> yeares.</p>
            <p>Th'other, hauing obtained of th'Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head the ſcepter of Italie, according to his patent proceeded, and got it by Conqueſt from <hi>Odoacer.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="494"/> But after he had reigned ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer <hi>30.</hi> yeares, deſcended alſo, leauing his fame and kingdome to his poſteritie, hauing fullfild his pleaſures two and fortie more.</p>
            <p>But this counſell pleaſed not th'other <hi>4.</hi> for as the verſe concludeth, they remained in other thoughts: drifting in their place to riſe and reigne, without leaue or licence of any.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>25</label> So I looked, and beholde, the vnder-winges thought to ſet vp them-ſelues, and to haue the rule.</q>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:8615:20"/>
            <p>And as the Prophet beheld the foure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary fethers which were left, he ſaw how they alſo ſtroue in their hearts to eſtabliſh them-ſelues, but like a dreame their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vaniſhed, in the next immediate verſes following.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>26</label> Then was ther one ſet vp, but shortlye it appeered no more.</q>
            <p>Then aroſe <hi>Odoacer,</hi> the firſt of the foure: leading a people begotten in the bowels and inmoſt parts of the North, who hearing of the deuided and weak eſtate of the Empire, was encouraged to moue from beyond the <hi>Danube,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="476"/> in much feare and blood deſcended into <hi>Italie,</hi> ſlew her laſt Lord and Emperor <hi>Momyllus Auguſtulus,</hi> deſtroyed the name of her Conſuler dignitie, and blotted out for euer the memory of her holy Senat, the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of <hi>Romulus</hi> their firſt King, and <hi>Iulius</hi> their firſt Keyſer: And not daring as baſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, to put on the preſence and ſtile of an Emperor (which name this fether fatallie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted) contented him-ſelfe with the title of <hi>King of Italie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But his glory indured not, for after he had reigned eighteene yeares, <hi>Theodorick</hi> (as in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8615:20"/>the <hi>24.</hi> verſe) tooke his kingdome from him by force, and his life by fraude: and he deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and appeered no more.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>27</label> And the ſecond, was ſooner gone then the firſt.</q>
            <p>After him aroſe <hi>Totilas</hi> the ſecond fether of the foure, by birth a Spaniard, by blood a <hi>Weſt-gothe,</hi> (whoſe fearefull fires burne in <hi>Rome</hi> to this day) but theſe daies were more in trouble, and (as the Prophet fore-ſaw) in number fewer then <hi>Odoacers:</hi> from his firſt riſing alway in armes, and after many hopes and as many diſpaires, was at laſt put to flight by <hi>Narſes,</hi> whom the Eaſt head had made gouernor of <hi>Italie,</hi> and flying was wounded ſo deadlye, that aſſone as he gat his Inne he loſt his life, after he had worne the crowne (if to fight for a crowne be to weare a crowne) <hi>11.</hi> yeares.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>28</label> Then I beheld, and loe the two that remained, did thinke alſo in them-ſelues to reigne.</q>
            <p>So as of all th'eight, ther remained but the <hi>Longobards,</hi> and th'<hi>inteſtine faction:</hi> which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8615:21"/>thought alſo in them-ſelues to reigne.</p>
            <p>The firſt inflamed by the letters of <hi>Narſes,</hi> and with the goodnes of Italie, left their northern dennes, and like a fearefull ſtorme fell down vpon it, and in two yeares ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw it,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="570"/> crowning their leader <hi>Alboinus,</hi> King thereof at Milan: who after he had ſpred him-ſelfe ouer the great Citie, and ouer all her <hi>Italie</hi> three yeares and a halfe, was murthered by the treaſon of <hi>Roſimond</hi> his wife, leauing his kingdome but not his honor to his ſucceſſors, who poſſeſſed it for <hi>24.</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p>The eight and laſt, and of all other the moſt dangerous, was <hi>a home conſpiracie,</hi> plotting to raiſe from the dead, the antient long-before buried gouernment of Rome, te reedifie her <hi>S.P.Q.R.</hi> And to root out the Prieſtly prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence and Church-ſuperiority, which had ſo cunningly eaten and deſtroyed the ſeculer: Which faction after it had taken fire in the hearts of many, and ſecretly burned a long time, at length brake out, like the fury and violence of a riſen ſtream, ſo as it might not be quencht, but with much blood and exceeding labor, as in the one &amp; thirteth verſe appeereth.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>29</label> But whilſt they ſo thought, beholde ther awaked one of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8615:21"/>heads that were at reſt, which was in the midſt, for that vvas greater then the tvvo</q>
            <p>And whilſt they thus thought, beholde there awaked one of the three Kingdomes, appointed to finiſh and end the wickednes of the Eagle, figuring by this reſting head, the new Weſt-Empire, which title of ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie the Beaſt beſtowed (as hath bin alwaies his practiſe to runne with the ſtrongeſt) vpon <hi>Charles</hi> King of France, and ſonne to <hi>Pepin</hi> the traiter. This head is ſaid to be awaked, when it was firſt rayſed, which was in the yeare <hi>801.</hi> wherein it receaued his auguſtal robe his crowne, and ſtile, viz. <hi>Carolo Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto a Deo coronato, magno &amp; pijſſimo Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tori Romanorum, vita &amp; victoria.</hi> And the title of dignitie Imperiall, which had laien dead aboue <hi>300.</hi> yeares, was in this yeare on Chriſtmas day, thus raiſed vp to life againe, to the end it might defend the proceedings of the great adulteres and murtheres of the earth, as by the forme of othe exhibited at his conſecration appeereth: <hi>In nomine Chriſti ſpondeo, atque polliceor ego A. Imperator, coram Deo &amp; beato Petro Apoſtolo, me prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorem, ac defenſorem fore huius Sanctae Rom. Eccleſiae, in omnibus vtilitatibus, quatinus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uino
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8615:22"/>fultus fuero adiutorio, pro-ut ſciero, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teroque.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that this head is ſaid to be in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, is ment, that it ſhould be choſen from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Nations and Kingdomes of the earth, as by experience hath bin proued: firſt from <hi>France,</hi> then from diuers kingdomes and parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> where it ſtill remaineth.</p>
            <p>And that the feare and power of this head hath bin greater, then any other Chriſtian King or Kingdome whatſoeuer, is it not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently read in the particular regiſters of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Nation?</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>30</label> And I ſawe, that the two heades were ioyned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</q>
            <p>By the two heads, are ſhadowed the two Kingdomes of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> whoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halowed leage the Prophet fore-ſeeing ſaith: they ſhuld be ioyned with this middle-head, and like three parts in one, accord and agree together, to humble themſelues, their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and power before the Beaſt, and for their Idol-ſhepheard ſhould fight againſt the Higheſt, till by the breath of his mouth they be ſcattered, like the duſt which the winde diſperſeth.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:8615:22"/>
            <p>And theſe ar the <hi>3.</hi> heads mentioned in the firſt, fourth, and ninth verſes of this chapter: and are therefore ſaid to finiſh and determine the laſt end and wickednes of the whore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe tho all other Kingdomes hate her and make her deſolate and naked, and eat her fleſh, as England, and others haue done: yet theſe three heads ſhall loue her ſtill, and to their dying day ſhall burne in delight with her, but when thoſe three and euery of them, ſhall alſo forſake her, ther ſhall not be found ether kingdome or creature vnder heauen, that ſhall fall down and worſhip her.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>31</label> And behold, the middle head was turned with them that were turned with it, and did eat vp the two vnder winges vvhich thought to reigne.</q>
            <p>And the Prophet ſaw this middle head (the head of euill,) impart his felowſhip to all Princes and Kingdomes, which deſired to be in leage with it. But my taske which haſteth to an end, will not ſuffer me now, and here, to ſound this gulfe of <hi>Santa Liega</hi> ſuffiſeth that for Syons ſake the Prophet paſſing by, doth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8615:23"/>point therat.</p>
            <p>And the Prophet beheld, that this middle head did deuoure &amp; eat vp the vnder winges, namely, the power of the <hi>Longobards</hi> and the <hi>inteſtine faction,</hi> which thought alſo to reigne.</p>
            <p>The firſt by the ſword of <hi>Charles,</hi> ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (for his exceeding power) the great, who at the command of Babylon his god, aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Italie, took her King <hi>Deſiderius</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and led him capture into France, and gaue his Kingdome to an other. And thus vaniſhed this ſeuenth contrarye feather, after it had humbled the whore, and ſpred it ſelfe ouer all her quarters <hi>200.</hi> and <hi>4.</hi> yeares, and the feare thereof diſcended, and it appeared no more.</p>
            <p>Th'other, firſt began in the daies of <hi>Cono</hi> the Emperor, who hauing an action of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary opinion, againſt <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſecond (for ſo the Beaſt was then called) followed it ſo hotly, that he brought his holines into ſuch diſgrace, as that he kindled a deſire in the hearts of many, to change their Prelat for a Prince, and to edifie their firſt and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient forme of gouernment againe. This deſire thus begun, by time (as naturally all conſpiration doth) gathered ſtrength, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured (but ſome-what to yong) to check the Beaſt, who by reaſon he was ſo well
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8615:23"/>guarded by his foreſaid head and champion <hi>Charles,</hi> eaſily neckt it. Notwithſtanding ſome <hi>100.</hi> and <hi>50.</hi> yeares after, this vleer now growen to a riper head, vnder the practiſe of one <hi>Alberique</hi> and <hi>Octauian</hi> his ſonne, brake out a new, and charged the Beaſt in ſo ſharp a manner, as without dout he had receaued the mate, had not his head in the mideſt auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it once againe, whoſe name was now changed from <hi>Charles</hi> the great, to <hi>Otho</hi> the great: who as being by oth deuoted, came to <hi>Rome,</hi> baniſht her new riſen <hi>Conſuls,</hi> hanged her <hi>Tribuns,</hi> and mounted her <hi>Prefectus vrbis,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of miſrule, naked on an Aſſe, crouned and attended through the citie with great deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: from thence committed to priſon, and ther executed with exquiſite torments.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="967"/> And by this means, the heat of this defection was ſo aſſuaged, that it appeered not for <hi>7.</hi> yeares after:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="974"/> but then (vnder the leading of one <hi>Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi>) flamed out a new, in ſo furious a ſort, as it had doutles fyr'd the Beaſt out of all his holds: had not his middle head (<hi>Otho</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond) haſted into Italie to quench the ſame: who (knowing how much it imported to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh exemplarly ſo dangerous an euill) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in the <hi>Vatican</hi> a ſumptuous feaſt, inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therto all the nobilitie and chiefe of the citie: when all were come, ſaluted and ſet: cauſed forth-with to be proclaimed, that no
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8615:24"/>man on pain of death, ſhould either ſpeake or moue at any thing that ſhould be ſeene or heard: preſently entred armed men and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed the place round where the gueſts were: wherat whilſt euery one amaſed, doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what this firſt courſe ment, this middle head drew forth a paper, and whoſe names were therein written, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to be drawen from the table, and in preſence of all there to be ſlaine. The reſt were curteouſly entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and were as merrie as the feare of ſo cruell a feaſte would giue them leaue. Ne yet for all this the feuer ſo lefte theſe patients, but that they fell ſome <hi>162.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1136"/> yeares after into relapſe againe, but <hi>Frederique</hi> the firſte (for ſo was now this head called) with the blood of a <hi>1000.</hi> and the wounds and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment of as many more, ſo branded this Hydra, which had bin ſo often headed, as it could neuer after recouer head againe, but her breath departed, and her purpoſe vaniſhed, and appeered no more.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>32</label> And this head did put the vvhole earth in feare, and ruled therein, and ouer the dvvellers thereof, vvith much labor; and it held the gouernment of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8615:24"/>vvorld more, then all the vvings that had bin.</q>
            <p>That this head and his fellowes, haue more mainteined &amp; aduanced the rage and blaſphemie of the Beaſt, then all the fethers that aroſe before them, and made more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and cunning inquiſition after the blood of Sion then they, is it not eternally croni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled in the regiſters of euery perticular Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? And therefore they are called the heads of the Eagle, and who knoweth not that heads are more able in euil then fethers? And the Prophet beheld that this head con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued longer, and held the gouernment of the world more then all the fethers that had bin, for from the riſing of the firſt fether <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> to the end and expiration of <hi>Momyllus Auguſtulus</hi> the laſt, were not <hi>560.</hi> yeares, whereas this head aroſe in the yeare <hi>801.</hi> and hath alreadie continued aboue <hi>800.</hi> and yet ſtill continueth, and ſhall, till he that now is be taken away.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>33</label> And after this I ſavv, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, this middle head ſodenlie vaniſhed as did the vvinges.</q>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:8615:25"/>
            <p>In that the Prophet ſaw this middle head ſodenly vaniſh, as did the winges, he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth that it ſhall not be rooted out by force or ſword of any, but depart quietlye, and die as it were in bed: but yet (as the truth fore-ſaith in the chapter following) <hi>not without paine:</hi> meaning, that the Electors ſhall not chuſe to the liking of the Beaſt, nor the Beaſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate to the liken of them. And in this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence this head ſhall die, ne ſhall this differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce be exempted from paine.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>34</label> But the two heads remained, vvhich alſo reigned ouer the earth, and ouer the inhabitants thereof.</q>
            <p>And when the power of this great head, (which is now ſo little) like a tale that's told ſhalbe cleane ended: yet the feare of th'other two ſhall ſtill remaine, and haue dominion ouer the earth, and thoſe that dwell therein, till the fulnes of their malice and tiranny be accompliſht alſo: which may not long be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulfild, for beholde, in the verie next verſe their diſtruction commeth.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>35</label> And I ſavve, and behelde,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8615:25"/>whilſt the head on the right ſide, deuoured that which was on the left.</q>
            <p>By the right head is ment (as through all this propheſie) the ſtrongeſt; ſo as the Prophet implyeth, that the ſworde of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſhall deuide the ſtrength of <hi>France,</hi> that her pride, by deuiſion made leſſe, may at the laſt (as euery deuided kingdome doth) returne to nothing. Nether ſhall the proſperitie of this right-head, be long free from like retaliation, but as the truth foreſaith.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Eſd.</hi> 4.12</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He that deuideth with the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword.</hi> For how may the ſword for euer eſcape him, whom heauen hateth, and earth doth perſecute? and of whom may be truly ſaid, which was ſpoken of Iſmael, <hi>Manus corum contra omnes, &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium contra illos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus ſhall theſe heads periſh, and haſt the faſter to their end, becauſe the iudgment of the Beaſt is nigh, in the very next verſes attending to come in.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>36</label> Then I heard a voice, vvhich ſaid, looke before thee, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the things vvhich thou ſeeſt.</q>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:8615:26"/>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>37</label> So I ſaw, and behold, as it were a Lyon came haſtily out of the wood, roaring; and I ſaw that he ſent out a mans voyce vnto the Eagle, and ſpake, ſaying:</q>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>38</label> Heare thou and I ſhall tell thee what the moſt High doth ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee.</q>
            <p>The roaring of the Lyon is the breath of the Higheſt, which ſhall rebuke th'Egle for her vnrighteouſnes, and caſt before her al her ſpoiles, and ſet her aliue in iudgement, and with the ſpirit of his mouth riſe vp againſt her, and lay vnto her charge, as in the text followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>39</label> Art not thou he which of the foure Beaſtes remaineſt, whome I made to reigne in my world, that by them th'end of thinges might come?</q>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>40</label> And the fourth is come, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8615:26"/>hath ouercome all the Beaſts that were paſt, and obtained povver ouer the vvorld vvith great fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, and ouer the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the earth vvith extreame oppresſion, and hath poſſeſſed ſo long time, all the vvorlde, vvith deceit.</q>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>41</label> For thou haſt not iudged the earth vvith truth.</q>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>42</label> But haſt troubled the meek and hurt the peacefull, and thou haſt loued lyers, and deſtroyed the dwellings of them which brought <hi>foorth</hi> fruit, and haſt caſt dovvne the vvalls <hi>of</hi> ſuch as did thee no <hi>harme.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>43</label> So <hi>as</hi> thy vniuſt dealing is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended <hi>to</hi> the moſt High, and thy pride vnto the mighty.</q>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:8615:27"/>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>44</label> And therefore he that is High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, hath beheld the proud times, and beholde they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and their abhominations are finiſhed.</q>
            <p>And if thou plead not guilty hereunto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, a thouſand witneſſes ſhall riſe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, and proue th'inditement true: that the iuſt iudgment which hath ſo long atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for thee, may at the length be pronounced againſt thee, in forme as in the text fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>45</label> Therefore appeere no more thou Egle, nor thy fearful vvings, nor thy vvicked feathers, nor thy malitious heads, nor thy cruell clavves, nor thy vaine bodie.</q>
            <p>And leaſt in thy drunkennes thou maiſt thinke, thy ſinne may ouer-ſhoot this iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come, and in thy madnes glorifie thy
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8615:27"/>ſelfe as thou haſt euer done, perſwading thy ſelfe thou ſhalt euer be, becauſe thou haſt bin king long, and like a foole haſt not conſidered; the more thy yeares the nigher thy graue, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, thus ſaith the truth: in the yeare which ſhalbe <hi>1666.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 13 18.</hi>
               </note> this iudgment here pronounced ſhall lay hands on thee. And as all thy feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full winges, and fethers, be already deſcended and blowen downe; ſo before that day (which is ſo nigh at hand) the tyrannie of thy mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious heads and cruell clawes, ſhalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed and brought to nought. And in that day, thy vaine body ſhall be burnt with fire, and ſhall ſo cleane be cut of from the land of the liuing, that neither ſonne nor nephew (as the Prophet ſaith)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 14.22.</hi>
               </note> nor branche nor remnant of thy name, ſhall be found vpon the earth. <hi>For as it is purpoſed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <hi>Eſay.</hi> 14.24.</hi>
                  </note> ſo ſhall it come to pas: and as it is conſulted, it ſhall ſtand.</hi> Goe to now, take counſell of thy Seers, and call thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters about thee: build thy deuiſes as high as heauen, &amp; lay their foundations low as hell, yet ſhal they not deliuer thee from the day appointed: but as <hi>Salmanazar.</hi> deſtroyed <hi>Beth-arbel</hi> in the day of battell, wherein the mother with the children was daſht in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: or like the milſtone, which the mightie Angell did caſt into the Sea, with ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſhalt thou be throwen downe, and be found no more.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:8615:28"/>
            <p>And all hell ſhalbe moued at thy comming and prepare it ſelfe, and raiſe by all her dead againſt that day to meet thee, and all the Princes and Kings of Nations, whom thou haſt ſlaine with the cup of thy fornication, ſhall riſe out of their torments againſt thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, and at thy ſight ſhall wonder, and cry,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 14.10.</hi>
               </note> and ſay vnto thee. <hi>Art thou become weake alſo as we? art thou become like one of vs? Is thy pompe bowed downe vnto the graue? and are thy pleaſures departed like ours? and is the worme ſpred vnder thee, and do the wormes couer thee alſo? how art thou falen from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> O Lucifer, ſonne of the morning, which haſt caſt lots vpon the Nations? and ſaidſt in thine heart: I will aſcend into heauen, and exalt my throne aboue, beſides the ſtarres of God, and I will ſit vpon the mount, euen the holy mount of his Sanctuarie, and Congregation: I will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend aboue the height of the clouds, and will be like the moſt High.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all hell, which once did wonder, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and kiſſe thy feet, beholding now thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, thy ſhame and iudgement, ſhall die for greefe of mind,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 14.</hi>
               </note> and dying ſhall ſay. <hi>Is this the man that made the earth to tremble? and with his worde did ſhake the Kingdomes? that made the world a wildernes, and a waſt of the Cities thereof?</hi> Then ſhalt thou lying in torment, death gnawing on thee, anſwere
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8615:28"/>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 5.</hi>
               </note>them and ſay. <hi>We haue erred from the way of truth, and the light of righteouſnes hath not ſhined vpon vs, nor hath the Sonne of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding riſen ouer vs. We haue wearied our felues in the wates of wickednes, and we haue gone through dangerous pathes, but the way of the Lord we haue not knowen. What hath pride profited vs? or what profit hath the pompe of riches brought vs? all theſe things are vaniſhed like a ſhadow and as a poſte that paſſeth by.</hi> And caſting vp thy eye to heauen, ſhalt ſee the righteous ſtand in great boldnes before thee, and before the face of ſuch as tormented the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and tooke away their labours, and thou ſhalt ware exceedinglie at the ſight of them, and be amaſed at their wonderfull deliuerance, and die for greefe of minde, and dying ſhalt ſay.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theſe are they whome we ſometime had in deriſion, and in a parable of reproche: wee fooles thought their life madnes, and their end without honor, But how are they counted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the children of God, and their portion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Saintes?</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>46</label> That all the earth may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, and come againe, as one deliuered from thy violen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that ſhe may hope for the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8615:29"/>iudgement &amp; mercy of him that made her.</q>
            <p>And thy death ſhall comfort and refreſh the earth, and deliuer Syon from her great and violent oppreſſion: but their proſperities may not longendure, as teſtifieth the Prophet <hi>Daniel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.12.</hi>
               </note> For may <hi>Iſrael</hi> dwell ſafe, and the Kings of th'eaſt not know it? Nay verily, they ſhall ariſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Ezec.</hi> 39.</hi>
               </note> and come down like a ſtorme, and like a cloud ſhall couer the earth, and compas round the tents of the Saintes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 20.9.</hi>
               </note> and the beloued Citie, till fire diſceud from God out of heauen (as it is written) and deuout them. And in thoſe daies ſhall be finiſhed the miſtery of God, fore-declared to his ſeruants the Prophets, and witneſſed by the mighty Angell which came downe from heauen, and ſtood vpon the Sea, and vpon the earth, and rayſed vp his hand and voice to heauen, and ſware by him that liueth for euer and euer. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Beholde it is come, and it is done ſaith the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <hi>Ezec.</hi> 39.</hi>
                  </note> this is the day whereof I haue ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the hope of which day, the ſtones of <hi>Syon</hi> die day by day: tho little eſteeming ſeuen thouſand deaths, in regarde of the preeious aſſurance ingrauen in their breſts, that they ſhall then and in that day, beholde the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:8615:29"/>hath ſo mercifully gathered them from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Nations: That hath ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preſerued them, from the ſorcerie of <hi>Babylon,</hi> which hath deſtroyed all the earth. That dayly leadeth them in and out, before the ſcorners, the couetous, and fooliſhwiſe of this world, ſo prudently, and ſo inuiſibly, that they ſeeing are not ſeene, and lyuing are not knowen. That hath beſtowed on them, a thouſand trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures more then theſe, ſo ſecretly, as no man ſuſpecteth but they that haue them. That hath ſo ſurely and fully perſwaded them, that tho they now goe on their way wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, yet they ſhall then returne againe with ioy, and bring the ſheafes with them: and all the earth ſhall then knowe, which now is hid, howe much the Lord their Redeemer loued them, and night and day, ſhall praiſe and magnifie the iuſte iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and mercie of him, that hath done all things for them.</p>
            <p>Which day in due time, He that is High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, ſhall manifeſt to all, He that is Prince an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>boue all, who only hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elleth in the light, which none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, whome no man
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8615:30"/>euer ſawe, nor can ſee: vnto whome be all ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ur and power euerlaſting.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Zachar.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Saue thy ſelfe O Syon, thou that dwelleſt with the daugher of Sebel.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:8615:30"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
